Ali MASRI

Nationality: Lebanese

(+1) 3203175412

Date of birth: 7 Feb 1991

Gender: Male

Website: <u>alimasri.github.io</u>

Skype: alimasri1991

• Address : Versailles (France)

ABOUT ME

I am a Research and Development Engineer dedicated to the field of Big Data and Artificial Intelligence. I have strong research and professional background with a Ph.D. degree in Computer Science from the University of Paris-Saclay and VEDECOM institute. In the domain of data science, I provide R&D services, consultancy services, and data science training.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Software architect

Cogent Softech [1 Jul 2020 - Current]

Address: Dearborn Heights, Michigan (United States) - http://cogentsoftech.com/

City: Dearborn Heights Country: United States

- o Create technical designs and functional models of software systems.
- o Design system architectures, modules and components related to the business' or customer requirements.

Research and Development Engineer

Cognitus/Intelligencia [1 Nov 2017 - Current]

Address: Paris (France) - www.cognitus.fr

City: Paris

Country: France

- Lead the Data Science team by monitoring and developing various AI and Big Data projects.
- Help customers optimize/upgrade architectures/pipelines by bringing in new Big Data and Al solutions.
- o Provide enterprise data science training to help customers build their own data science teams.

Researcher

VEDECOM [2015 – 2017]

Address: Versailles (France) - www.vedecom.fr

City: Versailles Country: France

- Research on transportation multimodality for smart cities
- o Proposed a new model to make multimodality easier to implement and maintain
- Proposed a three-level integration solution on:
 - Schema level
 - Data level
 - Services level
- o Implemented many software libraries as multimodal integration solutions
- o Published many articles in international conferences and journals

Backend and Mobile Developer

Logixy [Jan 2016 - Dec 2016]

Address: Paris (France)

City: Versailles Country: France

- o Business process design
- Database design and implementation
- Design and build a service oriented architecture using JAX-RS
- o Develop and integrate web application using Struts2
- o Develop and integrate an Android mobile application

Java Developer

3iConsulting [Jun 2015 - Dec 2015]

Address: Palaiseau (France)

City: Palaiseau Country: France

- Maintain and solve many bugs in a pre-built production solution
- o Implement helper tools for automating manual tasks

Research and Development

UVSQ and 3iConsulting [Feb 2014 - Jul 2014]

Address: Versailles (France)

City: Palaiseau Country: France

- Professional part related to my master thesis in supply chain management and service oriented architecture
- Help the company in adopt a service oriented architecture by designing and implementing a new version of a legacy logistics system

EDUCATION AND TRAINING

Ph. D. in Computer Science

Université Paris-Saclay

Address: Paris (France)

Masters in Information and Decision Support Systems

Lebanese University Faculty of Sciences

Address: Beirut (Lebanon)

Bachelors Degree in Computer Science

Lebanese University Faculty of Sciences

Address: Beirut (Lebanon)

PROJECTS

Eagle Eye - Intelligencia

Features:

- o A real-time solution for managing and monitoring Internet of Things video streaming devices.
- Runs state-of-art image\video analysis with the ability to deliver real-time reporting and alerting to clients.
- Easy-to-deploy architecture with interactive dashboard, android application and a companion application to extend the range of supported devices where no custom software could be installed.

Responsibilities:

- o Design and build an auto-scaling, extensible, and distributed event-based architecture
- o Implement the core event system using RabbitMQ and Python
- o Implement and extensible AI core that supports easy integration of pluggable AI models
- Implement, train, and deploy AI models plugins for face detection, face recognition, gender and age estimation, weapon detection, and object tracking.
- Implement a people tracking solution that integrates IOT location data with face recognition data to track movements of recognized entities.
- o Implement a REST API for managing the cluster and querying data
- Write technical reports and code documentation
- Manage the development of both the android mobile application the Angular web application

Lebanese License Plate Recognition - Intelligencia

- Manage the research and development process for investigating various recognition approaches for Lebanese license plates
- Implement a data generation algorithm to mimic Lebanese license plates data
- Implement a data processing pipeline using computer vision techniques and data augmentation that is trained on convolutional neural networks
- Implement an LSTM based approach using Connectionist Temporal Classification (CTC) loss
- o Integrate with YOLO for car and license plate detection
- o Deploy the system on a Django-based web application

ID Card Detection and Recognition - Intelligencia

- o Build a multi-step machine learning pipeline to detect and recognize ID cards information
- o Integrate a deep learning Card detection model
- Build a classification model to detect ID cards types
- o Build a preprocessing pipeline to denoise, un-skew and clean images
- Build a Region of Interest detection using generic and region-of-interest templates
- o Integrate with a fraud detection model for detect possible data change
- Implement a REST API for managing and querying the system
- o Implement a preprocessing pipeline for handling Arabic letters and digits

Enterprise Search Solution - Dar Al Handasa

- o Deliver a study report on existing solutions, and advise the best architecture that suits the client's needs
- o Organize and consult the implementation of an enterprise search solution using Apache Solr
- Build the complete data processing pipeline, while ensuring an incremental data extraction and integration
- o Deliver a best practices report for infrastructure configuration and implementation

Incremental ETL - Dar Al Handasa

- Design and implement an incremental Extract Transform Load (ETL) process from an existing data warehouse system into Hive under Hadoop Distributed File System (HDFS)
- Use Change Data Capture to read periodic updates into an Apache Spark processing engine
- Implement data versioning pipeline using Apache Spark
- Write processed data into Hive
- o Design Hive views to query fresh up-to-date data

Real-time Tweets Data Processing System - Al Jazeera News

- Use Apache Spark on Databricks to implement a high performance tweet collection and processing system
- o Implement a Spark Streaming solution that listens to new updates from Azure CosmosDB
- Use Scala for high performance computations
- Use Azure Cognitive Services to extract entities, keywords, and translate tweets
- o Implement custom pre-processing pipelines on tweets to extract hidden data in tweets

Intelligent News Gathering Platform - Al Jazeera News

- Design a system for fast news gathering and analysis based on Tweets
- Design and integrate a new solution using Events Hub, Databricks, CosmosDB, and Azure Cognitive Search
- Implement a dynamic, multi-layer filtering solution that uses heuristics and machine learning to filter irrelevant Tweets
- o Design feature engineering pipelines to extract user-based and tweet-based scores for filtration
- Implement a monitoring system that periodically updates pre-calculated scores based one new information
- o Integrate with real-time PowerBI dashboards

Festival Counting System - Intelligencia

- An extensible object tracking and counting system used to count and study the movement of crowd in festivals.
- The core system is developed in Python with the ability to choose any object detection method (YOLO, MobileNet, etc.)
- Use a centroid tracking algorithm to monitor objects movements
- o Implement a backend system that visualizes hot areas in a given map

Email to Odoo Task Automation - Logixy

- Implement a Python application that listens to new Gmail messages from a given sender, downloads and extracts fields from PDFs, and finally send extracted fields to an Odoo ERP instance.
- Use Google's Pub/Sub system to listen to new emails
- Implement a PDF fields extraction
- Implement an Odoo client that saves extracted information into their relevant tables
- o Implement a local folder watcher, to enable manual PDF uploads

DIGITAL SKILLS

JAVA / Python / Apache Spark / Deep Learning / Machine Learning / Git / Linux / Relational and Non-Relational Databases / Message Queues / Amazon Web Service (AWS) / Azure Machine Learning Studio / Microsoft Azure / Apache Solr / Azure cognitive search / Databricks / Event Driven Architecture / Compute r Vision / Natural Language Processing and Text Analytics

CERTIFICATIONS

Natural Language Processing Specialization by deeplearning.ai

https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/specialization/certificate/MTFTQAZB5PRT

IBM Data Science Specialization

https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/professional-cert/Y4RX82N2GBZQ

Deep Learning Specialization by deeplearning.ai

https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/specialization/XH5KKMY3RZDR

Machine Learning by Standford University on Coursera

https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/verify/9FPZPHCPS297

Google Developer Certification - Associate Android Developer

https://bcert.me/bc/html/show-badge.html?b=bsigjqw

HONOURS AND AWARDS

Lebanese Collegiate Programming Contest

LCPC

Placed 4th in the Lebanese Collegiate Programming Competition

Google Associate Android Developer Scholarship

Google

Receive a full scholarship for Google's Associate Android Developer Program

DRIVING LICENCE

Driving Licence: B

ONLINE PUBLICATIONS

Personal Blog

http://alimasri.github.io

Towards Data Science

https://towardsdatascience.com/search?q=Ali%20Masri

Heartbeat

https://heartbeat.fritz.ai/search?q=Ali%20Masri

Marktechpost

https://www.marktechpost.com/author/ali-masri/

The Startup

https://medium.com/swlh/search?q=Ali%20Masri

RESEARCH PUBLICATIONS

Ali Masri. Multi-Network integration for an Intelligent Mobility. Ph.D. Thesis.

https://tel.archives-ouvertes.fr/tel-01669051/

Ali Masri, Karine Zeitouni and Zoubida Kedad. Retry: Integrating ridesharing with existing trip planners. SIGSPATIAL2017

https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3140022

Ali Masri, Karine Zeitouni, Zoubida Kedad and Bertrand Leroy. An Automatic Matcher and Linker for Transportation Datasets. ISPRS2017

https://www.mdpi.com/2220-9964/6/1/29

Abdelfattah Idri, Mariyem Oukarfi, Azedine Boulmakoul, Karine Zeitouni, Ali Masri: A new time-dependent shortest path algorithm for multimodal transportation network. ANT/SEIT 2017: 692-697

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.procs.2017.05.379

Ali Masri, Karine Zeitouni, Zoubida Kedad and Bertrand Leroy. Automatic Detection and Mapping of Geospatial Properties in Transportation Data Sources. SIGSPATIAL2016

https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2996959

Ali Masri, Karine Zeitouni, Zoubida Kedad, Bertrand Leroy and Gabriel Kepeklian. Discovering Multimodal Routes using Connection Patterns. ITSC2016

https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/7795936/?reload=true

Ali Masri, Karine Zeitouni, Zoubida Kedad and Gabriel Kepeklian. Link++: A flexible and customizable tool for connecting RDF data sources. ESWC2016

https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-47602-5 22

Fatima Abdallah, Hassan Sbeyti, Ali Masri, Malak Khreis, Hussein Hazimeh, Mohamed Dbouk, and Ahmad Fadlallah: unified Sensor interface for Context-Aware Mobile aPplications (SCAMP). The Lebanese Association of Advanced Sciences LAAS20

Hamid Mcheick, Raef Mousheimish, Ali Masri, Youssef Dergham: Context Aware Collaborative Computing Model for Natural Disaster Management Systems. HCI (21) 2014: 439-449

https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-07788-8 41

LANGUAGE SKILLS

Mother tongue(s):

Arabic

English

LISTENING: C2 READING: C2 WRITING: C1

SPOKEN PRODUCTION: C1 SPOKEN INTERACTION: C1 French

LISTENING: A2 READING: A2 WRITING: A2

SPOKEN PRODUCTION: A2 SPOKEN INTERACTION: A2